<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd before the King on November the 13, 1686 being the feast of all the saints of the H. Order of St. Benedict / by ... Phil. Ellis ...</title>
            <author>Ellis, Philip, 1652-1726.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 48KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B21646</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11230046</idno>
  <idno type="VID">204920</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240895101</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E598</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11230046</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B21646)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 204920)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1440:38)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd before the King on November the 13, 1686 being the feast of all the saints of the H. Order of St. Benedict / by ... Phil. Ellis ...</title>
                  <author>Ellis, Philip, 1652-1726.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Published by His Majesties command."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Catholic Church --  Sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Festival-day sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:204920:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:204920:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd before the KING, ON <hi>November</hi> the 13. 1686. Being the Feast of all the Saints of the H. Order of St. <hi>Benedict.</hi> By the Reverend Father <hi>Dom. PHIL. ELLIS,</hi> Monk of the same Order, and of the <hi>English</hi> Congr. Chaplain in Ordinary, and Preacher to Their MAJESTIES.</p>
            <p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="license">
                           <p>
                              <hi>Published by His Majesties Command.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer to the King's Most Excellent Majesty, for his Houshold and Chappel. 1686.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:204920:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:204920:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preach'd before the KING On the 13<seg rend="sup">th</seg> of <hi>November,</hi> being the Feast of all the Saints of the Holy Order of St. <hi>Benedict.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Qui non accipit Crucem suam, et sequitur me non est me dignus. <bibl>
                     <hi>Matth. 10.36.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Aint <hi>John Chrysostom</hi> (most Sacred Majesty) speaking of the Devotion which the Church of his Age expressed to the Memory of the Saints, says,
<note place="margin">Nemo est qui nesciat, &amp;c.</note> There is nothing more known than the Reason why the Faithful
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:204920:3"/>are invited to assist at their Solemnities, that due Honour may be paid to them who have set before our eyes such bright and glorious Examples of Vertue, to excite us to a holy Emulation of their Glory,
<note place="margin">Chrysost. <hi>hom.</hi> 1. <hi>de Martyr.</hi>
               </note> Imitation of their Vertue; <hi>Vt et illis debitus honor dicetur, et nobis Virtutis exempla, favente Christo, monstrentur.</hi> And if this be the Sum of all our Devotion, if this be the end of all the Honour we exhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit to the Saints, it is a folly to apprehend <hi>Superstition,</hi> when <hi>the Service is so reasonable,</hi> or to fancy dangerous Consequences from Justice and Piety. For tho' we do not rank this practice of Venerating the Saints among the <hi>necessary</hi> Duties of Religion, yet if we desire to <hi>be Imitators of them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1.</note>
               <hi>as they were of Christ,</hi> as the Apostle advises in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to himself, Reason and Experience tell us, the best way to Copy out their Lives, and express a resemblance of them in our own, is often to contemplate these Beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and perfect Originals. The Church therefore on these Occasions opens a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble prospect to our view; On the one hand she shews what they suffer'd upon Earth; on the other, how largely they are rewarded in Heaven: Their Sufferings, to let us see
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:204920:3"/>the rigor of their Tryal; the Reward, to let us see the advantages of their Triumph: to the end that from the prospect of their Combat, we may draw Arguments of our Courage, Motives of our Sanctity; and from the consideration of their Triumphs, the hopes of our Glory. These two Views are admirably united in the words of my Text, where from the Negative, <hi>Who takes not up his Cross, and follows Christ, is not worthy of him,</hi> we learn, by the Rule of Contraries, who is worthy of him; He, only he, who takes up his Cross, and follows his Divine Leader. Taking up the Cross therefore is the <hi>Novice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship,</hi> carrying the Cross is the <hi>Profession,</hi> not only of the <hi>Monk,</hi> but of every <hi>Christian;</hi> and yet no more is required of the Monk, and yet no less of the Christian. I judge it therefore not improper, in an Age where Piety is at so low an Ebb, that it has left the Sands dry, almost without any hope of covering them again; where the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of Religion is not only laid aside, but the very Sentiments of it almost worn out of our minds; where Christianity at its full grouth, under Christian Princes and the shew of publick Exercise, is in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:204920:4"/>effect returned to its state of Infancy, fallen into its primitive Obscurity, and banish'd into Deserts and Monasteries; while People in the World have indeed <hi>the Form of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> assist at the Divine Service, joyn in the Formalities of Religion, but remit <hi>the Power thereof,</hi> the bearing the Cross, the pursuance of a penitential Life, to those who have renounced the World: I judge it not improper, I say, (with your Royal Permission and favourable Attention,) to dispute the case with these men, and to convince them from the highest Authority in Heaven and Earth, from Scripture and Fathers, and consequently from their own Reason and Belief, that the Secular Person has the same Obligations of tending to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as the Religious has; that all the <hi>Essential Duities</hi> are the same, the <hi>Method</hi> and <hi>Condition</hi> the same, <hi>Of taking up their Cross and following Christ.</hi> I accidentally touch'd upon this Matter the last time I appeared in this honourable Chair,
<note place="margin">Serm. upon Redeeming the Time.</note> and now it is my Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siness (I hope) to give them Satisfaction who found it not before. Let us beg the Divine Assistance, by the Intercession of these faithful Servants, who are now entred
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:204920:4"/>into the Joy of their Master; but we must apply our selves in a particular manner to the <hi>Queen of Solitaries</hi> whose blessed Retire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was Crown'd with that Angelical Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress, which deserves to be repeated by all who share in the fruit of it; <hi>Hail full of Grace, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE Eloquent Father of the Greek Church, (in his 36 Hom.) sticks so close to the Letter of this Text, that he will allow it to be taken in no larger a sense than the Words sound,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Carnem tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am morte affice &amp; cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifige. Nam quod illic operatur ensis, hoc hîc faciat prom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pta animi alacritas.</hi> Chrysost. <hi>hom.</hi> 11. <hi>in Epist. ad Hebrae. [in hunc loc.]</hi>
               </note> That every one is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd to live not only in a Disposition and Preparation of mind to die for Christ, but also to provide for the most painful Death, even that of the Cross; where he places the Force not upon the actual Effusion of Bloud (for then the Precept would not be general) but upon the practise of Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and the desire of Suffering for the Name of Christ. In this Sense the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of Fathers and Divines understand it; Particularly St. <hi>Hilary</hi> and <hi>Euthymius</hi> say, it is meant of our dying to the World: A Death St. <hi>Paul</hi> glories in our Lord he had
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:204920:5"/>already undergone,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.14.</note> before he had shed his bloud for the Profession of his Faith; <hi>The World,</hi> says he, <hi>is crucified to me, and I to the World:</hi> a Death he frequently ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and inculcates as necessary and universal: As <hi>necessary;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13.</note>
               <hi>If ye through the Spirit do mortifie the deeds of the flesh, ye shall live:</hi> where <hi>Mortification</hi> is expressed as the <hi>Conditional</hi> of Life eternal,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.24.</note>
               <hi>Si mortificaveritis, vivetis:</hi> As <hi>universal; They who are of Christ, have crucified the flesh, with the affections and lusts,</hi> the pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions and appetites thereof: where the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition is <hi>general,</hi> and from which none are exempted, but they who have <hi>no part in Christ; Qui sunt Christi.</hi> Now let the Wordling tell me, he cannot support Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication; and I must reply upon him, then he cannot be a Christian. Let the Lady tell me, she cannot deny her self that Liberty and Indulgence which suite with her State and Complexion, but I presume I shall not be thought rude for delivering the Mes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage which the Holy Ghost has put into my mouth,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.6.</note> and tell her in the Apostles Words, <hi>She that liveth in Delights, is dead while she liveth.</hi> Let the Courtier, if he pleases, object, he is not yet prepared for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:204920:5"/>works of Supererogation, he is not ripe for Mystick Divinity: but when he is grown weary of the World perhaps my Ascetick Lectures may make him an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorite: But for the present, <hi>non omnes capi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unt verbum istud, all do not take this word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 19.11.</note> and for his part he is one of them, and hopes to go to Heaven an easier way. An easier way than by following Christ! 'Tis impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible: or following Christ, and not carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Cross! 'tis absur'd. <hi>Non est me dignus;</hi> such an one is unworthy not only of being happy, but even of wearing the name of Christian; <hi>non est me dignus.</hi> For you will not find this discourse of our Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Redeemer address'd to Anchorites, or spoken to drive people out of the World, or limited to the Evangelical Counsels, or importing nothing beyond works of su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pererogation; The very stile of it speaks it a positive Command, a Law without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; <hi>If any one will come after me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 16.24. Marc. 8.35.</note> as St. <hi>Matthew</hi> words it; <hi>if any one will follow me,</hi> as St. <hi>Mark:</hi> Not directed only to the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, as St. <hi>Matthew</hi> seems to imply, but according to St. <hi>Mark, Convocatâ turbâ cum Discipulis suis, calling together the multitude
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:204920:6"/>with the Disciples,</hi> (the Antient Form and Method of publishing Laws) he Enacts this Penal Statute, he declares it to the multitude in presence of his Disciples, and and to his Disciples under the Testimony of the multitude: <hi>Si quis vult me sequi: If any one will follow me,</hi> of what condition or quality soever, <hi>let him deny himself and take up his Cross.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.23.</note>
               <hi>Dicebat autem ad omnes,</hi> saies St. <hi>Luke, he said to all</hi> present, and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence to all who to the end of the World should embrace his Doctrine, that no body should be excluded, provided always, <hi>he take up his Cross.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Such (Beloved Christians) are the terms of our warfare, the tryal of our obedience, the proof of our fidelity, and the argument <hi>That we have not believed in vain.</hi> But since it is not in every bodies power, as I said before, to fulfill it according to the Letter, by car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying the Material Cross with his Blessed Master, or actually shedding his Blood with the Martyrs, we are to learn from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text the genuine and proper sense of the Law. And, to the purpose, each of the Evangelists inserts a declaratory cause:
<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>abneget semetipsum:</hi> saies St. <hi>Matthew. Let him deny
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:204920:6"/>himself,</hi> implying self-abnegation to be the Catholick, the universal Cross, to which every one is oblig'd not only readily to sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, not only to bear it chearfully, but also to take it up voluntarily, by the Spontaneous exercises of a mortify'd and penitential Life. Tyrants, Enemies, and Persecutors may force other Crosses upon our shoulders, but this of self-denial can be laid on by no body but our selves. St. <hi>Mark</hi> puts the Equiva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, <hi>Deneget semetipsum,</hi> let him renounce himself, check his appetites, and curb his inclinations, and bridle his passions. In fine, St. <hi>Luke</hi> gives a farther light, by the addition of a <gap reason="foreign" resp="#oxf">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Let him take up his Cross daily,</hi> leading a dying life answerable to St. <hi>Paul's quotidie morior,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.31.</note> which gave the Holy Fathers occasion to define the life of a Christian,
<note place="margin">Hieron. <hi>Epis.</hi> 27 <hi>ad</hi> Eustoch. Anselm. <hi>In Epis. ad</hi> Rom. 12.</note> a daily Martyrdom, <hi>tota vita Christiani, si secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Evangelium vivat, quotidianum Martyrium est.</hi> S. <hi>Aug.</hi> Ser. 32. <hi>de Sanct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This indeed is <hi>a hard saying,</hi> a harsh sound, it is a thunderclap to one who has set up his rest here, or hop'd the profession of Christianity, did not proscribe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude all pursuance of pleasures, or had perswaded himself that an insipid Moral life
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:204920:7"/>which consists more in not doing evil, than in doing good, <hi>never denying it self, never taking up its Cross;</hi> but on the contrary, fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all that is painful and troublesome, will entitle him to Heaven: This is <hi>the</hi> word of God <hi>sharper than a two-edged Sword,</hi> to those who would faign believe that <hi>Jesus Christ came to send peace</hi> and repose <hi>on Earth.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10.34.</note> But he expresly tells us, he came <hi>not to send Peace but the Sword;</hi> a Sword <hi>which separates the Son from the Father, the Daughter from the Mother,</hi> forcing them from one anothers embraces, and cutting asunder the strongest ties of Nature and Affection, making them forget their Native Country, and their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers house,
<note place="margin">Psal. 44.11.</note>
               <hi>(obliviscere populum tuum, &amp; domum Patris tui)</hi> to spend their life in a voluntary exile, or solitude, which is a banishment at home. For as one <hi>who takes not up his Cross and follows me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10.37, 38.</note> saies our Divine Leader, <hi>is not worthy of me:</hi> So <hi>he that loves Father or Mother more than me,</hi> does not take up his Cross, <hi>non est me dignus,</hi> for <hi>he is not worthy of me,</hi> saies our Divine Legis-lator. This is the word, which from the tender age of Christian Religion, has peopled de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serts, has turn'd the most frightful Cavern into
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:204920:7"/>Oratories, has rendered the most inhospitable Sands, and almost inaccessible Rocks, not only habitable, but even delightful. This in fine, is that word, which to the amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of flesh and blood has brought down the most tender and delicate Daughters of <hi>Sion to sit in the dust,</hi> has drove the most tender and delicate complexions to macerate themselves with Fastings and Watchings, has summon'd the Courtier from his easie life, and Princes to quit their Purple and splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour for Sackcloth and Ashes. And I am perswaded, were it consider'd in cold blood, by the plurality of Christians,
<note place="margin">Nicephor. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>Hist.</hi> Eccles. <hi>c.</hi> 14. Pallad. <hi>in</hi> Lausia. <hi>cap.</hi> 25.49. <hi>&amp;c. Civitas in quâ plura erant Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steria quam prophanae domus; ita ut omnes vici, &amp; om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes anguli pleni essent Monachis divinas lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des decan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantibus.</hi>
               </note> it would soon convert our Houses into Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vents, our Villa's into Monasteries, and reduce our Towns and Cities into the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py condition of <hi>Nitria, Memphis,</hi> and <hi>Thebais,</hi> where History tells us, there were almost as many Religious, as inhabitants. At least, it would inspire another use of our Riches, than to hang Walls, cover Tables, stuff Cabinets or Coffers; they should be no longer the nourishment of our Vanity or Avarice, while objects of Charity lie at our doors, meet us in the streets, or the Widdow and Orphan cry from the Garret,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:204920:8"/>and the Seller, that you squander away in your very Equipage and Attire the ransome of your own Souls, and the blood of theirs; <hi>Sanguinem animarum pauperum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, Christians, mistake me not, I did not invite you to hear a Panegyrick upon the Holy <hi>Monks,</hi> whose Festival we celebrate this day; for tho the Renown of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestours be the Glory of the Posterity, and among the Ancients, the Son was upon some occasions oblig'd to commend the Parent, and publish his Merits in an Anni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versary Harangue to the people, yet this Roman vertue would savour of ostentation in a Christian, did not the Scripture war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant us <hi>to praise glorious Men,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccli. 44.1.</note>
               <hi>and even our Parents in their Generations; &amp; Parentes nostros in generatione suâ.</hi> I am sensible I might undertake this Province with little appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of affectation or vanity, since there is scarce any one within these Walls, or even upon English ground who is not particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly interessed in the Glory of the Benedictine Order; there is scarce an Antient Family, a Family of note which has not sent a Plant into this Nursery of Piety; there is not a Kingdom in the world, of what extent so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:204920:8"/>has transplanted so many Saints into Paradise, the major part of which, as far as the Church could take notice of them, and History could transmit their Memory, were still of the Benedictine Order: There is neither Order nor Nation,
<note place="margin">
                  <p n="1">1 St. <hi>Egbert</hi> first promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the <hi>German</hi> Mission, he reduces the <hi>Scottish</hi> Monks and Clergy to the due ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebration of <hi>Easter,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 By <hi>St. Maur</hi> and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 St. <hi>Aman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> Apostle of <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Gascony.</hi> 4 St. <hi>Willebrord</hi> first Arch-Bishop of <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trecht</hi> with eleven others, Apostle of <hi>Holland,</hi> and the adjacent Provinces: St. <hi>Swibert</hi> Apostle of <hi>Westphalia,</hi> the two <hi>Ewaldi</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, Apostles of the <hi>Frisons.</hi> 5 St. <hi>Boniface</hi> (alias <hi>Wilfrid</hi>) A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle of <hi>Germany,</hi> created Arch-Bishop of <hi>Mentz, An.</hi> 745. St. <hi>Stephen</hi> Apostle of <hi>Swedeland,</hi> St. <hi>Bruno</hi> of <hi>Prussia</hi> and <hi>Lithuania,</hi> &amp;c. 6 St. <hi>Nicholaus Anglus</hi> Apostle of <hi>Norway,</hi> &amp;c. 7 <hi>Spain</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duc'd from <hi>Arianism</hi> by St. <hi>Leander.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>V. Henr. Vander lipe de monachat. St.</hi> Greg. <hi>contra Card. Baron. &amp; Abb. Cajetanum de eod. V.</hi> Clem. Reyner <hi>Apostolat. Benedictin. Tract.</hi> 1. <hi>demonstr.</hi> 7. See the Testimonies of <hi>Sanders, Harpsfield,</hi> Card. Alan, Cotton, Selden, Spelman, Camden, <hi>ibid. pag.</hi> 201.</p>
               </note> which has sent out so many Apostles to propagate the Christian Faith; 1 <hi>Scotland,</hi> 2 part of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> 3 <hi>Flanders,</hi> 4 <hi>Holland,</hi> 5 <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> 6 <hi>Norway,</hi> and almost all the West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern Church on this side the <hi>Alpes,</hi> and 7 be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the <hi>Pyraenean,</hi> acknowledge these il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lustrious Men, all Benedictins, and most of them our Native Countrymen for the Founders, next under <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>storers of their Religion. I need not put you in mind of your Relation to some of these celebrated Men, I need not mention
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:204920:9"/>a St. <hi>Austin,</hi> and a long Succession of Arch-Bishops of <hi>Canterbury</hi> almost uninter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted till these latter times:
<note place="margin">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ex Regulari Concord. instituta in communi Concilio E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piscoporum &amp; Abbatum sub Edgaro Rege, Praesi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de S. Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stano Archie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pisc. Cant. ex Edmer Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileg. edit. a Selden. Cuncti de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creverunt ut Abbatum &amp; Abbatissarum Electio, cum Regis consensu &amp; consilio, S. Regulae ageretur documento: Episcoporum quo{que} electio, uti Abbatum, ubicun{que} in sede Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copali Monachi Regulares conversantur, si Domini largiente gratiâ tanti pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectus inibi monachus reperire potuerit, eodem modo agatur, nec alio quolibet modo, dum</hi> ejusdem <hi>sunt</hi> conversationis, <hi>a quoquam praesumatur. Si autem imperitiâ impediente, aut peccatis promerentibus, talis, qui tanti gradûs honore dignus sit, in eadem Congregatione reperiri non potuerit, ex alio noto Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorum Monasterio, concordi Regis et Fratrum, quibus dedicari debet, Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio eligatur.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Le decret du Saint Seige eut son effet, &amp; depuis cet Cathedrale (de l'Eglise de Cantorbery) eut pour Clergè une Communautè de Moines. L'Archevesque de Cantorbery en estoit l'Abbé regulier, &amp; il parvenoit a cette double charge par les suffrages de son Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitre, qui usa de ce droit d'Election jusqu' an regne d'<hi>Henry</hi> VIII. <hi>P. Mabillon, Abreg.</hi> de l'Historie de l'Ordre liv. 3. ch. 2. <hi>Maihew Troph.</hi> Congr. Angl. To. 1. pag. 12.</p>
               </note> Or a <hi>Melitus</hi> the first Bishop of this antient and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous City: You know that <hi>in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spel they begat you:</hi> And thô the Sun of Justice did shine before upon some part of this Island, yet, till the descent of these Luminaries upon it, your Ancestors, were not call'd to this <hi>admirable light,</hi> it was all night to them. And pray God, this Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of their Posterity, which by the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of another <hi>Ethelbert,</hi> and of another
<note n="*" place="margin">Called by St. <hi>Greg. Aldiberga.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>Bertha,</hi> ye behold Officiating at your
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:204920:9"/>Sacred Altars, may meet with some part of their success, under such Illustrious Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples; and may we, their unworthy Children, live up as near to the Sanctity of their Lives, as it is certain we keep up to the Purity of their Doctrine. I shall not speak of Men Famous in their ages for great Litterature and consummated Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, to whose Industry and Institution the Christian World owes the first pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Schools and Universities, particularly the two Eyes of this Nation, our two E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual Sisters. It would be as tedious to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, as stupendious to hear, how many Emperours and Kings, Queens and Emperes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses this <hi>Order</hi> has receiv'd into its Bosom: How many Bishops and Patriarchs it sent forth, and even Supreme Pastors,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> Arnald. Wion. Magn. Theatr. <hi>pag.</hi> 1084. Henr. Van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>lipe Praep. Affligenien. Haeften. ejusd. mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nast. praepo. in proleg. in Reg. St.</hi> Ben. Menolog. <hi>Benedictin.</hi>
               </note> who Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernd' the Church, and fill'd St. <hi>Peter's</hi> Chair for more than 300 Years: An account of these things is to be mett with in every History, they are known to the learned, and make but little to the Instruction of those who are not so: They are but the Fruits of their Labours, the Reward of their Sufferings, the Glory of their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity. But I am not designing <hi>a Catalogue
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:204920:10"/>of Honour,</hi> nor an Enumeration of their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatives, but your Imitation of their Vertues. Let us therefore take off our Eyes from the Beauty of the Fruit, the spreading of the Branches, and largeness of the Trunck, to consider the Root whence all these per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections spring, which you will easily agree with me without much Disquisition, is their taking up of their Cross, and following Christ; but how far this may concern you, I am going to let you see more plainly in my second Part.</p>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>SECOND PART.</head>
               <p>The H. Fathers and Ecclesiastical Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters expounding that Oracle of our blessed Master,
<note place="margin">Matth. 16.24.</note>
                  <hi>If any Man will come after me, let him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny himself, and take up his Cross, and follow me;</hi> generally found a Religious Institute upon this Text, for without the Observance of it, no Religious Order can have a being or sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sist.
<note place="margin">Trithem. l. 1 <hi>in Reg.</hi> S. <hi>Benedict.</hi>
                  </note> And indeed the Three substantial Vows are divinely couch'd, and insinuated in these Words. <hi>If any Man will come after me, let him deny himself;</hi> Self-denial infers, and chiefly consists in <hi>Obedience: and take up his Cross;</hi> the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:204920:10"/>and properest Crucifiction of the flesh, is <hi>Chastity: and follow me, pauper pauperem,</hi> importing a divesting our selves of all Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty, and putting on a true Apostolical Spirit, which enables us to say with them, who in Act had but little to leave, <hi>Behold, we have left all things,</hi> because they retained nothing, even in Desire. I judge it unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coming this Place, to go about to prove the lawfulness of making, or possibility of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming these Vows, which was never questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned but by those who had a mind to break them. They are in effect but the Repetition, with some Improvements, of what we all make in our Baptism, excepting that of perpetual Chastity, which the Examples of the Nazarites in the old Law, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Practice and Doctrine of the New de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrate not only to be possible, but also highly commendable, compared by our B. Original to the Life of Angels, who nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Marry, nor are given in Marriage. But you may ask me, what all this relates to you, who have neither given up your Wills, nor your Liberty, nor renounc'd the possession of Riches, nor of Pleasures as far as they are Lawful. <hi>multum per omnem mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum.</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:204920:11"/>It relates to you, not so much as to Religious, but very much still. For if you please to call to mind what I prov'd before, that the Substance of these Words, <hi>of denying your selves, of taking up your Cross, and following Christ,</hi> is a positive Commandment, tho the Extension of them, the <hi>ultimum quod sic,</hi> to what degree one may denie himself, is but a Counsel, you will find the Monk concern'd in them more as a Christian, than as he is Religious: and I suppose as Christians you will think your own Obligation equal to his. For there is no reason why it should be less, since in Jesus Christ there is neither Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant nor Freeman, but all are equally call'd to an equal Burthen; only you will find your own share more easy in appearance, but peahaps harder in performance.</p>
               <p>For if you inquire of the H. Fathers the best judges, because the best practitioners in a Religious Life, if you enquire of them in what the Vertue and Essence of a Monk consists, they give you no other account, than what the Scripture inculcates to all the Professors of the Name of Christ. If S.
<note place="margin">S. Basil. <hi>Serm.</hi> 3. <hi>Excr.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Basil</hi> say it is the Duty of a Monk, to be always mindful of his End, to rejoyce in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:204920:11"/>Hope, to bear Affliction, to Pray without ceasing, to give Thanks in all things, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test Arrogance and love Sobriety; it is no more than S. <hi>Paul</hi> exacts of every Christian, <hi>totidem verbis.</hi> If S.
<note place="margin">St. <hi>Bern. in spe. Monach.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>Bernard</hi> teach that a Monk must be like <hi>Melchisedec</hi> without Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or Mother, or Geneology, that is dead to all the interests of Flesh and Blood, our Blessed Saviour protests that <hi>who does not hate Father and Mother,</hi> that is prefer his Service to the Inclinations of Nature, <hi>does not hate even his own Soul,</hi> Postpone his Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Advantages and Propensions, to this great Duty, <hi>is not worthy of him.</hi> If St. <hi>Bernard</hi> define one who hates himself and loves Christ above all things,
<note place="margin">Serm. 15. <hi>de caend Domini.</hi>
                  </note> to be a true Monk: <hi>Qui propter Christum seipsum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, &amp; super omnia illum diligit, verè Mona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus est;</hi> yet this is deliver'd by our Saviour as the Definition of a Christian. If St.
<note place="margin">St. Isidor. Pelus. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 260.</note>
                  <hi>Isidore Pelusiota</hi> has reason to pronounce him a perfect Monk, <hi>si probus Monachus fieri studes,</hi> who lives not after his own manner, but will be accountable for his Actions to a Superiour, this is what the Apostle Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands every one, <hi>to obey your Superiours and be subject to them, for they watch over you, as
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:204920:12"/>being to give an account for your Souls,</hi> which they cannot do if you will not submit your Lives to their Censure. If Humility, as St. <hi>Bern.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>St.</hi> Bern. <hi>de ord. vitae. St.</hi> Machar. <hi>Hom.</hi> 15.</note> assures us, be the chief and Charact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eristical Vertue of a Monk, St. <hi>Macharius,</hi> (Hom. 15.) marks it out as the sign of Christianity it self, <hi>signum Christianismi est ipsa bumilitas,</hi> saies <hi>Macharius; suprema virtus Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nachi est ipsa Humilitas,</hi> saies St. <hi>Bernard.</hi> If a Monk be justly esteem'd dead to the World, and therefore the Common Law takes no more notice of him, as to any ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, than if he were not in being: So does the Law of Christ suppose every Christian dead to the World, so much the very Profession of our Faith imports, saies St. <hi>Bern.</hi> that we live not to our selves but to him who dy'd for us: <hi>Haec est professio fidei Christianae,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>St.</hi> Bern. <hi>Serm. de verb.</hi> Psalm. 23.</note>
                  <hi>ut qui vivit, jam non sibi vivat, sed ei qui pro omnibus mortuus est.</hi> To be short, if a Monk who lives irregularly in his Convent, or casts off his Habit to enjoy what he cannot now lawfully use, deser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly forfeits that Honourable stile: So St. <hi>Aug.</hi> in his admirable Book <hi>de vita Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ana ch.</hi> 11. warns us not to think him a Christian who performs few or no actions
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:204920:12"/>of Christianity, whose Conversation is not according to Justice, but tending to wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness and impiety;
<note place="margin">Aug. <hi>de doct. Anist. c.</hi> 11.</note>
                  <hi>ne illum Christianum putes:</hi> And elsewhere he tells us, he that is not a Christian is an Anti-christ; and gives us a general Rule how to discern true Christians from false: He is not a Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an who in his Life and Manners is contrary to Christ: <hi>non est Christianus qui vita &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus contrarius est Christo.</hi> The same affirms the grave and Eloquent <hi>Salvianus: Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ani esse dicuntur &amp; non sunt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. in spec. pec. c.</hi> 8.</note> they are said to be Christians but are not so, who by their Vices and Impurities render the very name of Religion Infamous.</p>
               <p>So far the Obligation is equal; let us now see wherein it is exceeding, and what is more requir'd of the Religious Man than of the Secular. This must be done by com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the Counsel with the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the special duty of the Monk with that which is common to him and the Laick. If it be a Counsel <hi>to sell all and give to the Poor;</hi> it is a Commandment,
<note place="margin">Psalm. 62.10.</note>
                  <hi>if Riches abound, set not your heart upon them.</hi> If it be a Counsel to dedicate ones self to the perpetual observance of Chastity, it is a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:204920:13"/>Command,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29.</note>
                  <hi>qui habent uxores, tanquam non habentes sint,</hi> let the Marry'd be as if they were not Marry'd; so great a Temper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Restraint of the Affections and Passions is enacted by the Law of Christ.
<note place="margin">Nolite dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere hunc mundum.</note> If it be a Counsel to forsake the World, it is a Precept <hi>not to love it:</hi> If it be a Counsel to renounce ones Possessions, it is a Precept <hi>to renounce ones self:</hi> if it be a Counsel to take the Monastick Habit, it is a Precept <hi>to take up the Cross,</hi> whatsoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver your state and condition be, to take it up <hi>daily,</hi> whatsoever your Business or Im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ployment. So that upon ballancing the two States, you will find your selves infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely disappointed, you will find the Life of the World more weighty and difficult than that of Religion; you will find the general Obligations the same, the Crosses more heavy and more frequent, but your necessity of bearing them, the very same, with this only diversity, that you must touch pitch, and not be defil'd, you must use the the World and be as if you us'd it not, you must cherish Creatures, but not love them, you must taste of pleasures, but must not enjoy them: and if it be incomparably easier to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stain
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:204920:13"/>then to contain, so it is by one heroical Effort to leap the Pale, and escape out of the World, then to live in a continual Jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardy, to stand ever upon the Guard, to have the sword at your Heart, <hi>and the Knife at your Throat;</hi> to tread the nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row Line upon the edge of Vertue so near the brink of Vice: for as S. <hi>Cyril</hi> of <hi>Alexandria</hi> observes, He that does every thing that is lawful, shall easily slip into what is unlawful. Whereas the great advantage of the Monastick State, is plac'd in furnishing those who embrace it with better means to compass the <hi>general</hi> End: it strengthens their Hands and puts better Arms into them, to fight against <hi>the Powers of Wickedness,</hi> it covers them with a Shield of proof against the most fiery Darts of Satan, it points them out a shorter cut to Happiness, by removing those Obsta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of Piety which so often occur in the World, and retard the course of Vertue, and by filling up, and levelling the Trenches the World had made to keep us in, and the Pit-falls to insnare us, that we may walk both more pleasantly and more securely.</p>
               <p>I know some will be very much sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priz'd
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:204920:14"/>at this Doctrine, as having imbib'd a quite contrary Notion of a Religious Life, figuring it to themselves like a Prison, a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy constraint and confinement, as intollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to freeborn minds as Dungeons, Fetters and Manacles; surrounded with Terrour and Solitude, resounding with the strokes of Disciplines, and ecchoing with the Sighs of unfortunate People, who out of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity, or perswasion, or force, are sold to a miserable Servitude, from which there is no Redemption. So like Hell do mistaken People picture the living Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentation of Heaven, the New Jerusalem descended from above, or at least a Copy of that glorious Original, a Transcript of the Life of Angels, as far as Nature, mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal and suffering, and surrounded with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmities, can admit. Where the Praises of God, and the Service of their Neighbour is the whole Business of the Inhabitants; where Mortification is a Delight, because desir'd; Poverty is Riches, because Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment; Obedience to the will of another is the greatest Pleasure, because attended with the greatest Security, and as easy in the Practice, as it is judg'd impossible in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:204920:14"/>Theory: where the Simplicity of the Diet contributes much to the Innocency of the Life, of which it is an Embleme; where people, saies S. <hi>Austin,</hi> grow familiar with Death, and so little fear it, that they can hardly refrain from desiring it, and when that happy Hour comes, they receive it with open Arms, an expanded Brow, and a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Mind, having nothing to leave be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them, but the prison of flesh, no other tye to break then the Union between the Soul and the Body, no other Settlement to make then to bid adieu to their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile, and return home.</p>
               <p>Here others will be no less surpriz'd then the former, as having been taught to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a very different Opinion of Monks, as Men ignorant, idle and unweildy, devoted to their Ease, indulging their Appetites, and fit to be out of the World, because they could be of no Service in it. This Judgment 'twas fit People should pretend to make of them when they began to covet their Possessions: when Avarice had opened their Eyes, it could do no less then discover them to be wicked Creatures, and Superfluous in Church and State, and prompt these Illuminate Zelots to rectifie
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:204920:15"/>the Errours and Mistakes of their Ancestors,
<note place="margin">Benefits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rising to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth from Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nasteries. V. <hi>Apost. Benedict.</hi> p. 217. Damages which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>su'd upon their Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression; bewailed by Learned Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants. <hi>V. Camden in Britan.</hi> 117. <hi>fuerunt etiam Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nante Henri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co octav. (Si fas sit memi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisse) avitae pietatis mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numenta, ad Dei Honorem, Fidei Christianae, bonarum{que} literarum propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, &amp; pauperum sustentationem, Domus Religiosae &amp;c. Statim circa ann. Henr.</hi> 8.36. <hi>in Remp. Angliae Ecclesiasticam, quasitorrens rupto aggere irru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it, qui Gentis Ecclesiasticae partem maximam orbe stupente, &amp; Anglia inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mente, cum pulcherrimis Aedificiis funditús prostravit redditus distracti, &amp; opes quas Christiana Anglorum pietas, ex quo primum Christo nomen dedisset, Deo consecraverat, quasi momento dispersae, &amp; absit verbo invidia, propha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natae. V.</hi> Bp. Godwin <hi>ad ann.</hi> 1540. Sr. William Dugdale <hi>in Monast. passim. &amp;</hi> Hist. Warwicksh. <hi>pag.</hi> 134. <hi>col.</hi> 1. But it was neither their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout &amp; strict lives; nor their charitable allowances that could preserve them from the common ruine <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> who by near a thousand years experience, found the Monks the Bulwark of Religion, and one of the most Serviceable Corporations to the Publick Weal. Poor Ignorant Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was of Opinion, That the first and chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est concern of Government, the very hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges on which it depends, was the Service of God. From performing which, with much personal Attendance, because the multipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicity of Affairs and Necessities of Life did hinder most People, she set Men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part whose sole Function and Calling it should be to Pray for and Instruct the rest, the Examples of whose Lives should sett a Beauty upon Piety, the stateliness of whose Churches, and convenience of Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion should rescue it from Contempt. But these Men of <hi>Dissolution,</hi> finding large
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:204920:15"/>Barns, forgetting they were the Granaries of the Poor; seeing spacious Fields, never reflecting they were the Patrimony of Jesus Christ; beholding Manificent Edifices, never considering they were Castles and Fortresses against Errours and Ignorance, within which Walls they themselves re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd, and to which their late Posterity was to ow it's Faith and Education; see<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing antient and well Furnish'd Libraries, whence the greatest Men both in Church and State have issu'd, and whither they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd in their Immortal Writings: Never minding, in fine, That those vast Piles of Building were the Mausolaeum's of their Ancestors, the surviving Monuments of their Piety, and the Repositories of their Sacred Dust; the Monks are to be charg'd with the Crimes of those who Condemn them; and their Houses raz'd to the Ground,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>V.</hi> Sr. Wil. Dugdale Hist. War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wickshire <hi>pag.</hi> 148. <hi>col.</hi> 1.157. <hi>col.</hi> 2.105. <hi>col.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libi passim.</hi>
                  </note> to deface the Memory, not so much of that Institute, as, of the Sacriledg committed upon it.</p>
               <p>But the loss of their Lands and Possessions was inconsiderable to them who had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing their own, who were but the Dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sers of the Publick Charity: a loss more
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:204920:16"/>Calamitous to the Publick then to them, and not to be regretted by their Posterity, if the same Hands which pull'd down their Houses had not bury'd their Innocence in the Rubbage. But this Posterity of theirs, which by a special Providence of God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>V.</hi> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stolat. Clement. Reyneri <hi>Tract.</hi> 2. <hi>ubi haec veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas stabilitur. V.</hi> Breve Pauli. V. Pont. Max. <hi>ibid in Append. script.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp; dat.</hi> 1612. <hi>Item aliud</hi> Breve <hi>ejusd.</hi> Pont. <hi>dat.</hi> 1619. <hi>ibid. script.</hi> 25. <hi>Item</hi> Bullam. Urbain. VIII. <hi>quae incipit</hi> Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tata. <hi>dat. ann.</hi> 1633. <hi>in Archiv. Congr.</hi> Matth. 18.18.</note> by an uninterrupted Succession to this very Day, through all the Revolutions and Changes which have swallowed up so many other Ecclesiastical Bodies and laid them in the dust, does willingly and freely Renounce all Titles or Rights which might <hi>possibly</hi> be inherent in the Antient and the present <hi>English</hi> Congregation of Monks, who ACKNOWLEDG by my Mouth, that the Alienation of their Lands, how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>just soever in the beginning, and ensuing Confirmations of it, is now fixed by so full and uncontrolable Authority both of CHURCH and STATE, that they can by no Law ECLESIASTICAL or CIVIL, be wrested out of the Hands of the present Possessours, or their Heirs. The Church, and, in her Name, the Supream Pastour, hath quitted all Pretensions, and Prays that what she has <hi>loos'd upon Earth, may be loos'd in Heaven;</hi> and that every one
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:204920:16"/>concern'd may enjoy as quiet a Conscience, as they do and shall to the end of the World, for her part, enjoy an undisturb'd Possession. The Supream Civil Magistrate, and the highest Court in this Realm, have, even with her consent, pass'd it into Law, which nothing, but the same Power that made it, can repeal. As for the Monks themselves, they, ever obedient to the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Temporal Powers, and tender of the Consciences of their fellow Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, not only <hi>willingly</hi> and <hi>without reserve,</hi> submit to this double Injunction, but also add a seperate RENUNTIATION of their own. They suppose no Judicious Person will question their <hi>Power</hi> to do it, more then a Conscientious person will question their <hi>Sincerity,</hi> that they have actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally done it. That Eclesiastical as well as Secular Corporations and Communities can <hi>Alienate,</hi> is certain And least it should be doubted whether they have made use of this Power, in a Case <hi>Prudence</hi> and <hi>Charity,</hi> and even <hi>Self-preservation</hi> so much require they again SOLEMNLY PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TEST, They desire nothing should be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stor'd but their REPUTATION, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:204920:17"/>to be thought by their Country-men, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Pernicious,</hi> nor <hi>Useless Members</hi> to their Country. And when I have in view the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles of Religion in this Kingdom, the Planters, the Propagators and Preservers of it; a <hi>Sigebert,</hi> an <hi>Alfred,</hi> and an <hi>Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,</hi> and many others, once Powerful Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs in this Island, who postpon'd the Purple to the Cowl: when I contemplate a S. <hi>Erminburga,</hi> a S. <hi>Eanfleda,</hi> an <hi>Editha,</hi> an <hi>Eleonora,</hi> with many others, once Glorious Queens in this Island, who prefer'd the Humility of a Monastique Habit, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scurity of a Cell to the Pomp and Splendor of a Court: When I behold, I say, so ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Royal Advocates appearing in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of their Order, I will suppose so just a cause is gain'd, so reasonable a request is granted.</p>
               <p>But to conclude this Discourse, I must re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the first, in this Place the third sort of Men, who think as much too well of a Monastick State, as the others do too ill, and would needs confine all the serious Practice of Religion within the Walls of a Cloyster. Talk to them of doing Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for their sins, they reply, That's the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:204920:17"/>life of a Monk: Exhort them to Mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, they send you to Preach to those who have renounc'd the World: Tell them of Fasting and Praying, and parting with their superfluities, they cry, you drive us to dispair. But I must needs advertise these People, that they are engag'd in a more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Errour, than the others, who vilifie and contemn the Claustral Life. For those hope no Spiritual Advantage from it, and therefore stand upon their own bottoms: These hope too much, as if the Prayers and good Works of other Men, would exempt them from performing what is so Essen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial to a Christian, and indispensable to a Sinner. Whom then did Jesus Christ threaten, <hi>unless you Repent, you shall all perish?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 13.3.</note> Whom did he Command to Pray without ceasing? To Visit the Sick, to Comfort the Afflicted, to Relieve the Poor, to do Good to those that Persecute you, to Bless those that Curse you; and, in fine, <hi>to take up your Cross and follow him?</hi> If these Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands were directed to all, all who take them not home to themselves, <hi>are not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of him.</hi> Unhappy Men who think any thing too hard to compass Heaven!
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:204920:18"/>Foolish Men who think Eternal Glory may be purchas'd at a lower rate! Childish Men, who call this Doctrine the Subject of their dispair, which is the only Foundation of their hope!</p>
               <p>Let us not accuse the weakness of our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; we have never try'd what Nature as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sisted by Grace can do, what it can support, but we see it in the Examples of these Saints, once as infirm and frail as our selves; they were form'd of the same Earth, and by the same Hand, many of them indeed of a better mould, Vessels of greater Honour, but, to our Confusion, they stoop'd to Acts of Humility which the meanest of us thinks beneath him: And one of the Reasons why their Relicks are plac'd upon our Altars, is to put us in mind, that the persons we so much admire, are not above our Imitation.</p>
               <p>Let us not alledge the inequality of our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and the difficulty of acquiring Vertue in a Secular and distracted Life, since Divine Providence has set Patterns for every State within it's own verge: Neither do we so much revere a <hi>Sigebert</hi> or an <hi>Alfred</hi> in a Cloyster, as we Admire a <hi>Constantine,</hi> an <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> upon the Throne: Nor a <hi>Cunigundis</hi> in the Habit of a Nun, as a <hi>Bertha</hi> or <hi>Aldiberga</hi> in
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:204920:18"/>the State of a Mighty Queen. And thô there are no <hi>Court-Saints</hi> in Heaven, yet blessed be God, there are many Courtiers; not only a <hi>Cassiodorus</hi> who abandon'd it, but an <hi>Ethelred</hi> with a Train of Nobles, thô but few in every age, who continu'd in it all their daies, yet a Court seems a Contradiction, at least a great Impediment to Sanctity, thrô the Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and Softness (to say no more) which are hardly separable from it, <hi>Ecce qui mollibus,</hi> &amp;c.
<note place="margin">Matth. 11.8.</note> The Camp too hath produc'd many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessors as well as Martyrs, as well those who took Arms for the safety of their King and Country, as others who laid down their Lives for Justice sake: Not only those who quitted the Military for the Monastical Cincture, but innumerable others who ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd to an eminent degree of Sanctity in that very Profession, in which, to the confusion of these times, most people loose what they had acquir'd before. In fine, S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us there is <hi>a cloud of Witnesses</hi> to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw and baffle our weak Defence, Court Arguments, and Popular Excuses,
<note place="margin">Hebr. 12.1.</note>
                  <hi>impositam habentes nubem Testium.</hi> You know a Cloud is not gather'd in a Moment, neither is all the Rain or Dew which falls carry'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:204920:19"/>wards again, and restor'd to it's former Eleva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Sun Extracts and Sublimates the finer parts, and leaves the rest below. So does the Sun of Justice, he Raises e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Soul according to the proportion of his Grace and her yielding to his Influence and following his Attractions: The grosser and more sensual minds he leaves in the Earth they love, and precipitates them whither their affections carry them. <hi>Amor tuus, pondus tuum,</hi> thy love is thy weight, saies St. <hi>Austin; si terram amas, terra es:</hi> If you love the Earth, you are Earth; <hi>si coelum amas, coelum es,</hi> if you love Heaven, you are part of it, and shall be happy for ever in it; which I beseech, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:204920:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>